Guide to the DJ Screw Papers
University of Houston Libraries
DJ Screw Papers
1975-2006
1994-2000
06/2010-023
DJ Screw, 1971-2000
4.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Personal papers, photographs, creative material and technology, sound recordings, and promotional material comprise the DJ Screw Papers.
Biographical Information:
DJ Screw was born Robert Earl Davis, Jr. on July 20, 1971, and he began DJing and making mixtapes as a teenager while living on the Southside of Houston. By the early 1990s, Davis began to develop his innovative “chopped and screwed” technique of using recording technology to repeat phrases (a process known as chopping) and slow a song’s tempo (known as screwing). Davis became known as DJ Screw and distributed “screw tapes” featuring his technique.
As the popularity of the “chopped and screwed” technique grew, DJ Screw began to receive requests to make tapes tailored for friends and local rappers, often to celebrate an event such as a birthday. These tapes would include a selection of slowed down tracks, shoutouts by DJ Screw, and freestyles by rappers over the beats at the beginning and end of the tapes. To create the “chopped and screwed” effect on these tapes, DJ Screw simultaneously played two copies of the same record on a turntable and slowed each down using the turntable’s pitch control function. He then used the crossfader to switch between the records to repeat beats, words, and phrases. This process would create a master cassette. DJ Screw would then slow the tempo further by using a four-track’s pitch control function to manipulate the master cassettes and produce the final tape. He began selling copies of these “screw tapes” or “grey tapes” (so called because of their color) from his home.
The screw tapes helped to develop the careers of numerous local rappers, who would subsequently become known as the Screwed Up Click (S.U.C.). Prominent members of the S.U.C. included the Botany Boys, Fat Pat, HAWK, Lil’ Keke, E.S.G., Big Pokey, Big Moe, Lil’ O, Al-D, Yungstar, and Lil’ Flip. The music of the S.U.C. often addressed local culture, particularly the city’s custom car culture and the use of recreational drugs, especially marijuana and codeine.
DJ Screw achieved broader popularity in the mid-1990s, and he continued to sell tapes while releasing four studio albums on Bigtyme Recordz: “All Screwed Up,” “3 'N The Mornin' (Part One),” “3 'N The Mornin' (Part Two),” and “I Wanna Get High with Da Blanksta.” As a member of Dead End Alliance (D.E.A.) with Fat Pat, HAWK and Kay-K, he also appeared on the album “Screwed for Life.” In 1998, DJ Screw opened the store Screwed Up Records and Tapes in order to meet demand for his mixtapes.
On November 16, 2000, DJ Screw was found dead in his recording studio at the age of 29. His death was ruled an overdose of codeine and other drugs. The “chopped and screwed” genre that he created continues to influence recording artists, both locally and nationally, and his legacy is honored by fans around the world.
Sources:
DJ Screw: The Untold Story. Double Platinum - Come Fly With Me, 2006. DVD.
DJ Screw Photographs & Memorabilia Digital Collection description. University of Houston Digital Library. 20 March 2013. http://digital.lib.uh.edu/collection/djscrew
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Screwed Up Click (Musical group)
Genre/Form of Material:
Audiocassettes; Ephemera; Financial records; Personal papers; Posters
Personal Name:
DJ Screw, 1971-2000
Topical Term:
Disc jockeys -- Texas -- Houston; Hip-hop -- Texas -- Houston; Hip-hop -- United States; Rap (Music) -- Texas -- Houston; Rap musicians -- Texas -- Houston
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research. Some materials have been restricted for privacy reasons. Where possible, surrogates with sensitive information removed have been filed in place of the originals.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Related Materials:
DJ Screw Photographs and Memorabilia digital collection (http://digital.lib.uh.edu/collection/djscrew)
DJ Screw Sound Recordings (https://library.uh.edu/search/?searchtype=a&SORT=D&searcharg=DJ+Screw+Sound+Recordings&searchscope=11)
Physical Characteristics or Technical Requirements:
Due to the fragility of the original screw tapes, they cannot be played directly. Digital copies of screw tapes 1-5 can be accessed in the Special Collections Reading Room by advance request. These materials may require up to one week to access. Contact Julie Grob (jgrob@uh.edu) for more information.
Scope and Contents
Personal papers, photographs, creative material and technology, sound recordings, and promotional material comprise the DJ Screw Papers. DJ Screw’s activities as a DJ and mixtape creator are the focus of the papers, and materials documenting these activities include lists for his screw tapes, sound recordings, production materials, including recording equipment, business documents, and photographs. All materials were owned by DJ Screw and donated by his father, Robert Earl Davis, Sr., unless otherwise noted.
This collection includes materials containing personal, financial, and contact information for DJ Screw and his associates. Access to these original materials is restricted in order to protect privacy, but some materials have publicly-available surrogates filed in place of the originals.
Detailed List of Contents
- Personal Papers
  - Correspondence and Funeral, 1999-2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Funeral service programs, November 24, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 1)
    - Greeting card to Nikki [Williams], undated (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 2)
    - Greeting card to Screw from Nikki [Williams], undated (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 3)
    - Letter from Meledy Mathis to DJ Screw stating that they are cousins, May 24 1999 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 4)
    - Greeting card to Nikki [Williams] from LaWanda, undated (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 5)
  - Financial Documents, 1998-2000
    - Tuxedo receipt for Stick 1’s wedding, April 30, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 1)
    - Personal financial documents [RESTRICTED], 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 2)
  - Contact Information and Notes, undated
    - Pocket memo notebooks containing phone numbers and notes with lyrics [original notebooks RESTRICTED; surrogates of notes available in collection], undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 1)
    - Post-it note regarding Kazy D’s request for DJ Screw to make a mix [RESTRICTED; surrogate available], undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 2)
    - Black Entertainment Television, Inc. business card, undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 3)
    - FUBU business card, undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 4)
    - Goodfellas Entertainment Co. business card, undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 5)
    - Addition figures note totaling 129.75, undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 6)
    - Slips of paper with personal phone numbers [RESTRICTED], undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 7)
- Photographs
  - DJ Screw playing baseball for the Pirates, [Smithville, Texas?], approximately 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 1)
  - DJ Screw (front left) and teammates playing baseball for the Pirates, [Smithville, Texas?], approximately 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 2)
  - DJ Screw with his mother, Ida Mae Davis, his grandmother, his sister, Michelle Williams, and his niece Shameka [Gift of Nikki Williams], June 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 3)
  - DJ Screw with unidentified rap duo, for whom he DJ’d, approximately 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 4)
  - DJ Screw and DJ Chill behind their turntables at a middle school dance at Gregory Lincoln Education Center [Gift of DJ Chill], approximately 1992 (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 5)
  - Maestro at Samplified Digital Recording Studio in Missouri City during the recording of “3 ‘n the Mornin’” [Gift of DeMo], February 22, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 6)
  - DJ Screw at Samplified Digital Recording Studio during the recording of “3 ‘n the Mornin’” [Gift of DeMo], February 22, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 7)
  - Rappers Al-D and DeMo at DJ Screw’s house on Greenstone [Gift of DeMo], February 23, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 8)
  - DJ Screw on the mixer and turntables in the recording room in his house on Greenstone [Gift of DeMo], February 24, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 9)
  - DJ Screw’s remains at his funeral, Houston, November 24, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 10)
  - DJ Screw’s car restored with his portrait on the hood during a Screwfest event, Pasadena Convention Center and Fairgrounds, July 22, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 11)
  - DJ Screw and friends with a platinum record [Gift of Nikki Williams], undated (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 12)
  - Shanian, daughter of Shetoria (Tori) from “9 Months Later” tape, undated (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 13)
  - Unidentified woman, undated (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 14)
- Music - Screwed Up Click
  Scope and Contents
  Digital access copies of the original screw tapes 1-5 can be accessed in the Special Collections Reading Room. Contact Julie Grob (jgrob@uh.edu) for more information.
  - Screw Tape Lists, [1999-2000?], undated
    - Screw tape list for Lil’ Keke [RESTRICTED; surrogate available], [1999?] (Box 1, Folder 5, Item 1)
    - Screw tape list for Steve [Big Steve of Woss Ness?] [RESTRICTED; surrogate available], [1999?] (Box 1, Folder 5, Item 2)
    - Screw tape list for Soc, with DJ Screw’s tick marks next to songs, indicating that he had recorded them, [2000?] (Box 1, Folder 5, Item 3)
    - Screw tape list, undated (Box 1, Folder 5, Item 4)
  - Lyrics, undated
    - Rap lyrics by Shunny Pooh written during a visit to DJ Screw’s house, undated (Box 1, Folder 6, Item 1)
    - Unidentified rap lyrics, undated (Box 1, Folder 6, Item 2)
    - Unidentified rap lyrics, undated (Box 1, Folder 6, Item 3)
  - Business Documents, 1996-1999, undated
    - Mix Wiz Disc Jockey Association feedback form filled out by DJ Screw, February 19, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 7, Item 1)
    - Budget for DJ Screw, D.E.A., and Southside Playaz appearance at Sixth Street Fat Tuesdays (2 copies), April 11, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 7, Item 2)
    - Request for five tapes with money order and envelope, August 31, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 7, Item 3)
    - Another Screwed Up Productions shipping envelope from Dirty Harry Productions, undated (Box 1, Folder 7, Item 4)
    - “State and Federal Posting Requirements for All Texas Employees” order form for Screwed Up Records and Tapes, undated (Box 1, Folder 7, Item 5)
  - Financial Documents, 1994, 1996, 2000
    - Soundwaves receipt for $5.40, June 12, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8, Item 1)
    - Soundwaves receipt for $121.14, June 26, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 8, Item 2)
    - Packing list receipt for WEA Manufacturing for Lump of On the Level Promotions, January 19, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 8, Item 3)
    - Soundwaves receipt for $211.39, March 12, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 8, Item 4)
  - Sound Recordings
    - Screw Tapes Belonging to Others
      Item 1 is a screw tape that was created by DJ Screw for Lil' Randy, and distributed directly to Lil' Randy.
      - 99 Live screw tape made for Lil’ Randy [cassette tape] [Gift of Lil' Randy] [CANNOT BE PLAYED], 1999 (Box 2, Item 1)
    - Screw Tapes Belonging to DJ Screw
      Items 2-5 are thought to be original cassette tapes (master screw tapes) from the live recording sessions, prior to being slowed down during the audiocassette duplication process used to produce the final screw tape. They were donated by DJ Screw's longtime girlfriend Nikki Williams. Items 5-14 may be a mix of master screw tapes and dubs. They were acquired from Screwed Up Records & Tapes.
      - “Da Freestyle King’s” tape made for Lil’ Flip [Gift of Nikki Williams] [CANNOT BE PLAYED], undated (Box 2, Item 2)
      - “Da Return” tape made for Lil’ Keke (songs on tape match track list for "P's and Q's" [Gift of Nikki Williams] [CANNOT BE PLAYED], 1996 (Box 2, Item 3)
      - “Leanin on a Switch” tape made for Big Pokey [Gift of Nikki Williams] [CANNOT BE PLAYED], undated (Box 2, Item 4)
      - “Sittin on Chrome” tape made for Slick Rick [Gift of Nikki Williams] [CANNOT BE PLAYED], undated (Box 2, Item 5)
      - "3 Years Later" tape [CANNOT BE PLAYED], undated (Box 2, Item 6)
      - "Facin Time" tape made for Mark [CANNOT BE PLAYED], undated (Box 2, Item 7)
      - "Ghetto Fabulous" tape made for Big Steve [CANNOT BE PLAYED], undated (Box 2, Item 8)
      - "Hurricane Duck" tape [CANNOT BE PLAYED], undated (Box 2, Item 9)
      - "Killuminati" tape [CANNOT BE PLAYED], undated (Box 2, Item 10)
      - "Making Cash Forever" [CANNOT BE PLAYED], undated (Box 2, Item 11)
      - "Ohh Wee Man" [CANNOT BE PLAYED], undated (Box 2, Item 12)
      - "Platinum Shit" [CANNOT BE PLAYED], undated (Box 2, Item 13)
      - "Shit Don't Stop" [CANNOT BE PLAYED], undated (Box 2, Item 14)
  - Recording Equipment, undated
    - Maxell tape label, blank (Box 1, Folder 9, Item 1)
    - Superscope Technologies, Inc. feedback form for CDR device, blank (Box 1, Folder 9, Item 2)
    - Addendum instructions to CD recorder (Box 1, Folder 9, Item 3)
    - User guide to Marantz stereo double cassette deck (Box 1, Folder 9, Item 4)
    - Realistic portable amplified speaker used by DJ Screw during the mixing and recording process (Ovs item 1)
    - Stanton stylus (Box 3, Item 1)
  - Promotional Material, 1996-2002
    - Big Mello promotional photograph to accompany the release of his 1996 album “Southside Story” on N-Terrorgation Records (Box 1, Folder 10, Item 1)
    - Tire & Wheel Connection II and Car Tek Audio presents its 4th Annual Car & Truck Show and Concert flyer, featuring Houston rap groups and artists 20-2-Life, 380, Criminal Element, Woss Ness, Big Love, Lil' Keke, and "D" of Trinity Garden Cartel, Texas Southern University, August 10, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 10, Item 2)
    - Juneteenth Rap Explosion concert flyer featuring D.E.A., Southside Playaz, and Straight Profit Records, Vernon L. Richards Riverbend Park, Smithville, Texas, June 19, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 10, Item 3)
    - On Da Grind Records presents Big DeMo June 27 Birthday Jam All Access Pass for the third anniversary of DJ Screw’s most famous screw tape, June 27, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 10, Item 4)
    - Flyer for "New Album Release Party featuring Lil Flip, Sucka Free Records, & Botany Boys, Big Shot Records”, February 19, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 10, Item 5)
    - DJ Screw “Sentimental Value” handbill, approximately 2002 (Box 1, Folder 10, Item 6)
    - Southside Playaz, You Gottus Fuxxed Up sticker, approximately 1998 (Box 3, Item 2)
    - Lil’ Keke, The Commission, poster flat, approximately 1998 (Box 3, Item 3)
    - South Park Mexican, Hustle Town, approximately 1998 (Box 3, Item 4)
  - Mix Tapes Song List, approximately 2001
    - Hanger with track listing for the 713-390-5979 BOXX radio request line [Postdates DJ Screw], approximately 2001 (Box 5, Item 1)
- Music - Non-Screwed Up Click
  - Promotional Material, 1995-2001, undated
    - BMC Distribution packing list promo enclosure, undated (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 1)
    - Brian McKnight “Mercury Times” flyer, for Mercury Records, with envelope, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 2)
    - Chubb Rock, “Beef,” flyer, [1997] (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 3)
    - Dark Sun Riders, “Dark Sun Riders,” flyer, [1996] (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 4)
    - “The Devil in the Mirror” audio film, flyer, undated (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 5)
    - Evil Minds, “Thank You Adam,” sticker, [1998] (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 6)
    - Ghetto Mafia “In Decatur” remix, flyer, [1998?] (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 7)
    - J’Roll, “Vibin On The Hood,” flyer, [1997?] (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 8)
    - Legal Substanz, “One Nation Under a Game,” flyer, [1998] (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 9)
    - Mass 187, “Real Trues Paying Dues,” sticker (3 copies), [1995] (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 10)
    - Master P (Colonel), “No Limit Soldiers compilation,” sticker, [1998] (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 11)
    - Milk Promotions, flyer, undated (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 12)
    - Mr. D.O.G. “Ghetto Politics,” handbill, [2001] (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 13)
    - Mr. Quikk, the South’s #1 D.J., Dirty Harry Productions, handbill (2 copies), undated (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 14)
    - Shot Callers, “Ya Only Live Once,” handbill, [1999] (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 15)
    - Speed Knot Mobsters, “In Your World,” flyer with envelope, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 16)
    - Spragga Benz, “Good Day” remixed by KRS 1, flyer, undated (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 17)
    - Too Short, “Cocktails,” promotional bullet, [1995] (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 18)
    - Trick Daddy, “www.thug.com,” postcard, [1998] (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 19)
    - Bone Thugs-n-Harmony, The Art of War, poster flat, [1997] (Box 3, Item 5)
    - G-Ride, “Comin atta Black Pitch,” poster flat, [2000] (Box 3, Item 6)
    - Geto Boys, “The World is a Ghetto,” poster flat (2 copies), [1996] (Box 3, Item 7)
    - Ruffhouse Records, note to Rose “to hit retail with upcoming LP”, undated (Box 3, Item 8)
  - Print publications
    - Ebony magazine, Vol. 53, No. 4, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 12, Item 1)
    - Murder Dog magazine, Vol. 6, No. 3, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 12, Item 2)
    - Murder Dog magazine, Vol. 7, No. 1 (2 copies), 1999 (Box 1, Folder 13, Item 1)
    - Right On! magazine, Vol. 26, No. 10, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 13, Item 2)
    - What It Dew magazine, Issue 6, [2000?] (Box 1, Folder 14, Item 1)
    - XXL magazine, Vol. 2 No. 4, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 14, Item 2)
  - Audiovisual Material
    - DJ Screw's Audiovisual Material
      - Southsyde Connxshun featuring La Sno and Stylz, Raise Da Roof – Push It Up (Call It What U Want) VHS tape, undated (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 1)
      - Big Ron Da Don, “Chillin’ Finna Make a Million,” unlabeled cassette tape (Box 2, Item 6)
      - E-40, “Federal,” cassette tape (Box 2, Item 7)
      - Midwest Syndicate, “The Compilation,” cassette tape (Box 2, Item 8)
      - Bumbino, “The Story of a Young Socrates,” cassette tape (Box 2, Item 9)
    - Promotional albums sent to DJ Screw
      - Christyle, “Land of Milk and Honey”, 1998 (Box 4, Item 1)
      - Fiend, “Talk It Like I Bring It,” from “Street Life” (2 copies), 1999 (Box 4, Item 2)
      - Fredro Starr, “Dat B Dem”; Haystack, “Reckon” (2 copies); Majic Juan, “Te Jodiste” (2 copies), 2000 (Box 4, Item 3)
- Personal Ephemera
  - Black & Mild cigar wrapper (Box 1, Folder 15, Item 1)
  - Dickies advertisement, undated (2 copies) (Box 1, Folder 15, Item 2)
  - Radius car promotional flyer, undated (Box 1, Folder 15, Item 3)
  - English homework of Doug Jones, with references to DJ Screw, undated (Box 1, Folder 15, Item 4)
  - Houston 3 Parole office Black History Month programs (2 copies), February 23, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 15, Item 5)
  - WAR event calendar, March 1999 (Box 1, Folder 15, Item 6)
  - Funeral service program for Clifford Mapp, February 4, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 15, Item 7)
  - Crown Royal bag (Box 3, Item 9)